划
Pull!
他已经死了 扔下去
He's gone. Put him over.
长官
Sir.
噢 你好 乌利纳斯
Salve, Vorenus.
- 你还好吗 - 还好
- How are you? - Good enough.
- 水 - 谢谢
- Water. - Thank you.
我曾经站得那么高
I was far away.
我一辈子
All my life...
都很害怕失败
I've been fearful of defeat.
现在我真的败了
But now that it has come,
却不如我想象中的可怕
it's not near as terrible as I'd expected.
太阳照常升起
The sun still shines.
水还是那么甘甜
Water still tastes good.
荣耀只是过眼云烟
Glory is all well and good, but...
我们曾经活过就够了 是吧？
life is enough, ne?
捷报! 在希腊的亚克兴角
Glorious news! At Actium, in Greece,
我们的最高执政官屋大维·恺撒派出的海军
the navy of our imperator Octavian Caesar
在马库斯·维普撒尼乌斯·阿格里帕 的指挥下
under the command of Marcus Vipsanius Agrippa
赢得了决定性的胜利
has won a decisive victory
击败了克娄巴特拉女王
over Queen Cleopatra
还有她的奴隶马克·安东尼
and her slave Mark Antony.
埃及舰队全军覆没
The Egyptian fleet has been destroyed.
现在 屋大维·恺撒 正向亚历山大挺进
Even now, Octavian Caesar advances on Alexandria
那个妖妇和她的 小跟班在那儿避难
where the witch and her creature take refuge.
显然 战争一开始 克娄巴特拉就吓得躲了起来
Apparently, Cleopatra took fright and fled as soon as the battle started.
那个胆小的恶棍安东尼 也跳上船追随她而去
And that cowardly villain Antony jumped in a boat and chased after her.
留下他的兵士 为了他的淫欲而去送死
Left his men to die for the sake of lust.
安东尼不是懦夫 他们一发现赢不了
Antony's no coward. As soon as they knew they'd lost the battle,
就转而保全克娄巴特拉船上的黄金
they fled to save the gold that they'd stowed on Cleopatra's ship.
无疑 他们还想继续打
They plan to fight on, no doubt.
没钱可不行
They cannot do that without money.
- 不是懦弱 - 我丈夫不是这么说的
- Wasn't cowardice. - That's not what my husband says.
你丈夫在撒谎
Your husband's a liar.
哎呀
Dear me,
你到底帮哪边？
one might wonder whose side you're on.
他小时候可不是这样 曾经他是个多么诚实的孩子
He wasn't like that as a child. He was a good honest boy.
究竟是怎么了
I don't know what happened.
也许我一直错了
I'm to blame, probably.
如果您保证克娄巴特拉 和她的后裔能继续保有王位
If you maintain Cleopatra and her progeny on the throne,
马克·安东尼阁下发誓
his honor Mark Antony, by his sacred oath,
将会结束其政治生涯
will withdraw from public life.
并在埃及隐居
He will reside quietly in Egypt as a private citizen
他还承诺永不参与政事
and promises never to engage in any way whatsoever with politics...
跟他说不可能 他得无条件地把他自己和他女人的命交到我手里
Tell him no. He will put himself and his woman in my hands without conditions.
是的 阁下
Yes, sir.
安东尼身边有个人 名叫卢修斯·乌利纳斯
There is a man close to Antony. His name is Lucius Vorenus.
我要你私下跟他说
I want you to speak to him alone.
提图斯·波罗在这
Tell him Titus Pullo is here
能保证他的安全 只要他能想办法打开城门
and will answer for his safety if he can find a way to open the gates.
你可以那么跟他说 但他不会照办的
You can tell him that, but it won't do any good.
有什么话他一听就知道是你说的？
Is there some word we could send him that he knows comes only from you?
波罗 如果有必要 我会烧了皇宫 和里面的一切
Pullo, if need be, I will burn down the palace with all inside.
跟他说他的孩子都很好
Tell him that his children are well
而且我希望我的孩子也很好
and that I hope my child is well also.
我们之间的笑话 他能明白
Private joke. He'll understand.
说
Speak.
盖厄斯·屋大维·恺撒阁下声明
His honor Gaius Octavian Caesar
他拒绝您的请求
states that his answer is no.
就这样？
That's all?
他要求您和您的人民无条件投降
He demands that you surrender yourself and your people without conditions.
镇定
Calm.
我很镇定
I am calm.
我是很镇定
I am.
你去跟他…
You go and tell...
跟那个小畜生说
that frog-spawned homunculus...
- 我… - 镇定
- that I... - Calm.
我们得保持镇定
We must remain calm.
乌利纳斯 带他去喝点什么
Vorenus, find this man a drink or something.
要我投降 他说
Surrender, he says.
我宁可吃了自己的孩子 也不会向他投降
I'd sooner eat my own children than surrender to him.
我们可以在晚上化装出逃
We could escape by night in disguise.
我们可以到南边去
We could go south
然后…
and...
然后躲在草丛里
And hide under bushes
像被追猎的野兽那样？
like hunted animals?
不 不 我不能逃
No. No, I cannot run.
你做什么我都跟着 当然了
I will be guided by you, naturally,
如果你还有别的办法
if you think there is some other path available to us.
死
Death.
我们可以死
Death is available to us.
难道就没有什么兵法
Is there not some military trick,
什么计谋能让我们脱困吗 你对这些是最擅长的啊
some clever ruse to turn things about? You're so good at that sort of thing.
噢 流血和撒尿没有区别 女人
Oh, piss and blood, woman.
我是个战士 不是什么魔法师
I'm a soldier, not a fucking magician.
看看我们周围
Look around us.
妓女 同性恋
Whores, hermaphrodites
还有马屁精
and lickspittles.
组成我们现在的军队
This is our army now.
这些…
This...
就是我们仅有的了
is all we have left.
提图斯·波罗说你的孩子很好
Titus Pullo says that your children are well.
他希望他的孩子也很好
He hopes his child is well also.
他说这是你们之间的笑话 你能明白
He says it is a private joke that you'll understand.
- 那么他来了？- 在恺撒身边
- So he's here? - And close to Caesar.
他负责保证你的安全
He answers for your safety
假如你离开安东尼 并想办法打开城门
if you will forsake Antony and find a way to open the gates.
你跟提图斯·波罗说 他的儿子很好
You tell Titus Pullo that his son is well...
但他忘了我是谁
but he has forgotten who I am.
也许你该考虑一下
Maybe you should think on it a while. What other way...
否则… 你 特使
You, emissary.
挑战
A challenge.
我与你的主人
I challenge your master...
- 一对一单挑 - 阁下？
- to single combat. - Sir?
他与我面对面 带上刀剑和盾牌
Let him meet me face to face with sword and shield,
像我们的祖先那样决斗
just as our ancestors did.
我们会知道 谁更强
Then we shall see who is the better man.
- 安东尼 - 不要劝我
- Antony. - No.
只有这个办法了
This is the way.
他怎么能拒绝？
How can he refuse?
他的尊严难保
His honor is at stake.
他必须得接受 否则别人都会认为他是个懦夫
He must accept, or he will be exposed as a coward.
去告诉他 告诉他营地里的所有人
Go tell him. Tell everyone in his camp.
马克·安东尼向那个小王八蛋 下了战书
Mark Antony has called the dog out.
跑着去
Run!
乌利纳斯...
Vorenus...
备好武器 我们得练习练习
fetch some weapons. We shall practice.
- 乌利纳斯 - 殿下
- Vorenus. - Highness.
屋大维会杀了我
Octavian's going to kill me,
是不是
is he not?
他们还在谈判 你不会有事的
They're negotiating. It'll be all right.
别骗我
Do not lie to me.
恺撒大帝只能有一个儿子 如果必须得有一个死 一定是我
There can only be one son of Caesar. If anyone dies, it will be me.
说大声点儿 让老天爷听到 会把它当成你的愿望来满足
Talk that way loud enough, the gods'll hear you and they'll make it so.
跟我去兵器库 找把像样的剑配你
Come with me to the armory. We'll get you a decent sword.
如果真的打起来 你能学以致用
If it comes to a fight, you can give as good as you get.
单挑？
Single combat?
- 用刀剑和盾牌 - 他疯了吗
- With sword and shield. - He's gone mad, has he?
我觉得他像是醉了 或者被下了药 大人
I'd say more drunk or drugged than mad, sir.
克娄巴特拉呢 她也是这个样子吗
What of Cleopatra? Is she in the same condition?
不是的 大人 她很清醒 谨慎
No, sir. Sober, alert.
- 卢修斯·乌利纳斯呢 - 对安东尼仍旧非常忠诚
- And Lucius Vorenus? - Remains loyal to Antony.
谢谢 到外面待命吧
Thank you. Stay close by.
那就打下来 我去跟工兵说
A siege, then. I'll inform the engineers.
就算是个疯子 也能死守那皇宫 几个星期 甚至几个月
Even a madman could hold that palace for weeks, months.
- 那烧了它 - 我们得让埃及人民保持沉默
- Burn it down, then. - We need to keep the Egyptian people quiet.
我估计 把他们的女王 和皇宫一起毁了 会激起民愤
I suspect destroying the royal palace with their queen inside might make them rather peevish.
那该怎么办
What, then?
这个是给你们的女王的
This is for your queen alone.
只给她一个人看 明白吗
No other. Is that clear?
是的
Yes.
够了
Enough.
你觉得我很好笑？
I amuse you?
不是的 大人 你觉得我很好笑…
No, sir. I assure you...
我是他妈的小丑 是吗
I'm a fucking clown, am I?
噢 我该…
Shall I...
我该给你跳个舞 是吗？
Shall I do a little dance for you?
- 这样你满意了吗 - 殿下…
- Does that please you? - Your highness...
站起来
Stand up.
把你的剑和盾牌给他
Give him your sword and shield.
- 我们来看看他是不是比我厉害 - 安东尼
- Let's see if he can do any better. - Antony.
别 嘘 嘘
No.
给
OK?
拿着
Take them!
- 女王陛下 求您了 - 别求她
- Queen Majesty, please. - Don't look to her.
在这儿 我才是主人 拿好
I'm the master here. Now take them.
准备好了吗
You ready?
真的 殿下 我只是为了自保
Really, sir, I must protest.
好啊
Yes!
年轻的赫耳墨斯又回来了
Young Hermes has returned.
那小子怎么说？
So, what does the boy say?
我们什么时候碰面？
When do we meet?
大人 屋大维·恺撒…
Sir, Octavian Caesar...
恭敬地…
respectfully...
拒绝了您的挑战
refuses your challenge
并且重申之前的条件
and asks the same terms as before.
如果您不答应 明天开始我们会采取火攻 并且包围整个皇宫
If those terms are not accepted, fire and siege works will begin tomorrow.
你叫他 和他的这些条件都去吃屎
You tell him to shove his terms up his arse.
好小伙儿
Good lad.
懦夫
Coward.
他妈的懦夫
Fucking coward.
他一直是他妈的懦夫
He always was a fucking coward.
你们在看什么？
What are you all looking at?
玩儿你们的 一堆人渣
Enjoy yourselves, you scum!
吃啊
Eat!
吃啊 吃啊 吃啊
Eat! Eat! Eat!
喝酒 音乐
Drink! Music!
来跟我喝一杯
Come and have a drink with me.
现在你们看到了吗？
Now do you see that?
看到了吗 你们这群埃及贱民
Do you see that, you gyppo cunts?
真正的罗马人是这样喝酒的
That is how a real Roman drinks.
致克娄巴特拉·腓罗柏多女王陛下
"To her majesty, Queen Cleopatra Philopator.
我很清楚 您会陷入如此困境
"I fully understand that you have been led
并非由于您的决定错误
"into this predicament through no fault of your own
而是因为马克·安东尼那个叛徒
"by the renegade Mark Antony.
如若您能将他交付于我
"If you will deliver him to me,
无论他是死是活 我向您发誓
"either alive or dead being no matter,
在任何情况下
"I promise to you on my oath
您和您的人民都会毫发无损
"that you and your people will be unharmed
并且得到恭敬的外交礼遇
"and treated with all respect.
您能保留您的王位 和所有在这块大陆上能行使的权利
"You shall retain your crown and all continent rights."
他向我提出会使自己遗臭万年的要求
He asks me to bring eternal dishonor on my name.
可是反过来
And in return,
您的帝国
your empire,
您的人民 储君的生命都得以保全
your people, Majesty's life.
以我的名誉换我的生命
My life for my honor.
够公平了
Good enough.
- 总比死了好 - 答应就等于做了他的奴隶
- Better than death. - That is a slave's answer.
陛下感觉到了死神的呼吸
Majesty has felt Anubis breathe on her before now.
她知道她的选择是对的 她想要活下去
She knows her slave is right. She wants to live.
你在这儿啊
There you are.
你在做什么 嗯？
What are you doing here?
回去狂欢吧
Come back to the party.
等一会儿吧
Maybe later.
怎么了 可怜的宝贝儿 你很难过吗
What's the matter, poor baby? Are you sad?
我当然难过
Of course I am sad.
你看看你
Look at you.
看看我们
Look at us.
就像阿波罗和伊希斯 真可悲
Apollo and Isis, it's pathetic.
对不起 我不是那个意思
I'm sorry. I do not mean that.
不
No.
不 你说的对
No, it's true.
我们在一起的这些年
These years together
是我一生中最快乐的时光
have been the happiest of my life.
我们曾经爱过 对吗？
We lived, didn't we?
是的
We did.
屋大维明天会烧了皇宫
Octavian will burn the palace tomorrow.
我们得决定如何结束这一切 还有什么时候结束
We must decide how to end this, and when.
好的
Yes.
为什么不现在就结束呢
Why not now?
不 亲爱的 我们不要在黑暗中死去
No, dear, let's not go in darkness.
等到明天 在阳光下…
Tomorrow in the sunlight.
明天
Tomorrow.
客人在等我们
Shall we go back to our guests?
我不去了
No, I'm tired.
我累了 你去吧 没关系的
You go. I don't mind.
只去一小会儿 好吗
Just for a little while maybe.
他有一副美妙的歌喉
He had that lovely singing voice.
在日尔戈维亚 从眼睛里拔出长矛
Took a spear in the eye in Gergovia.
噢 嗯 是的 甘撒 是的
Yes. Gansa.
他…他怎么样？
What of him?
我忘了
I forgot.
去他的
Fuck him.
你相信人有来世吗
Do you believe there is an afterlife?
当然有
Of course.
很多人说没有
There are people who say no.
这辈子就是全部
And this is all there is.
- 谁说的 - 博学的人
- Who says that? - Learned men.
- 希腊人 可能 - 希腊人？
- Greeks, probably. - Greeks?
希腊人说的都是废话
Greeks talk a whole pile of nonsense.
都去死吧
Fuck 'em.
马克·安东尼
Mark Antony.
大人
Sir.
怎么了
What's happened?
我的最爱
"Dearest love,
原谅我这样离开你
"forgive me for leaving you this way.
你知道我最不想说再见
"You know how I hate to say goodbye.
在另外一个世界 我们会重逢
"I will see you again on the other side.
求你 快点来
"Please, come quickly."
我的爱人
Sweet...
为 为什么她…
Why didn't...
为什么她不等我
Why didn't she wait for me?
女王必须独自死去 这是惯例
The queen must die alone. It's the custom.
她在死前叫了您的名字
With her last breath she called your name.
请你 出去
Please, you go away now.
那么就这样吧
Here it is, then.
有什么东西能解决 我这个多活了一夜的混蛋
Anything to be rid of this fucking hangover.
这把不行
This won't do.
得用把真正的罗马剑 嗯？
Let's use a proper Roman sword.
这是把该死的好剑 嗯？
It's a damn good sword.
不管怎么说 在这里死去也挺好的
It's a good place to die, at any rate.
好过死在高卢的沟渠里
Could have been a ditch in Gaul.
认识亚历山大的人
Men that knew Alexander...
曾经站在这里
once stood here.
我想 是比很多地方要好
Good a place as any, I suppose.
卢修斯·乌利纳斯…
Lucius Vorenus...
我的生命已到尽头
I enter the end.
你别跟我死在这
Don't you die here with me.
只要有可能就逃出去
You get out while you can.
我会的
I'll do that.
能为您效劳 我很荣幸 长官
It's been an honor serving with you, sir.
真的吗
Has it?
我 我希望是如此
I hope so.
握紧了
Brace it there.
还有什么指示或者口信吗 长官
Any instructions or messages, sir?
没有了
No.
告诉人们我死得很体面
Just tell the people I died well.
以罗马人的方式死去
I died Roman.
噢 我可怜的爱人
My poor love.
带孩子们过来
Bring the children.
卢修斯·乌利纳斯有话要说吗
Lucius Vorenus wishes to speak?
- 没有 - 那他就不该继续盯着我
- No. - Then he shall stop looking at me.
- 我命令你 - 我无须服从你的命令
- I gave you an order. - I take no orders from you.
我没取你的命是因为 安东尼喜欢你
I let you live because Antony was fond of you.
现在你看我敢不敢杀你
Do not test me now.
你还有脸
Kiss my arse!
我没让你开膛破肚算你走运
You're lucky I don't open your stomach.
我不知道为什么你没有 光荣地追随你的长官而去
I wonder that you had not done the honorable thing and followed your captain.
噢 我会的
Oh, I would.
但我得把小恺撒带走
But I have to get Caesarion out of here.
- 你说带走是什么意思？ - 他不走 屋大维会杀了他
- What do you mean? - If he stays, Octavian will kill him.
他很安全 我跟屋大维有协议
He's perfectly safe. I've made a pact with Octavian.
我保有王位 他不会伤害我的人
I keep my crown and no harm will come to my people.
屋大维可能会让你活着
Octavian may let you live
戴着皇冠在广场上游行
so he can parade you through the Forum in your crown.
他会对安东尼的孩子 表示同情和关心
To Antony's children, he will show public mercy and kindness.
但是对于小恺撒 恺撒大帝的另一个儿子
But Caesarion, another son of Caesar,
- 屋大维会杀了他 - 不
- Octavian will kill him. - No.
- 他只是个孩子 - 他会死
- He's just a child. - He'll die.
为什么 嗯？我们都知道 他不是恺撒大帝的儿子
And for what? We both know he's not the son of Caesar.
我们什么都不知道
We know nothing of the sort.
你做那种勾当之时 我在场
I was there at his conception.
你说什么都没用
Doesn't matter what you say.
他就是恺撒大帝的儿子
He is the son of Caesar.
不管他是谁 留在这 他就会死
Whoever he is, he stays here, he dies.
如果没有被你的求生欲望蒙蔽 你一定也能看得出这点
You'd see that if your desire to live hadn't blinded you.
那你呢 你为什么要救他 他是你什么人
And you, why would you save him? What is he to you?
他跟我没关系 但他父亲是我的朋友
He's nothing. But his father is my friend.
我会把孩子带给他
I'll take the boy to him.
- 那个男人 叫什么名字 - 提图斯·波罗
- The man, what's his name? - Titus Pullo.
是的
Yes.
- 他是个好人吗 - 你怎样定义好人？
- Is he a good man? - Define good.
孩子们 来
Children, come.
看
See.
亲手结束自己的生命
By his own hand.
这样才死得高贵
That is how nobility dies.
收拾好行李
Put on your traveling clothes.
为了安全 你得跟 卢修斯·乌利纳斯一起离开
You're leaving with Lucius Vorenus for your safety.
可是这里是我的家 跟你在一起
But my place is here with you.
穿上你的旅行衣
Traveling clothes now.
谨致吊唁之意
My condolence for your loss.
他死的很安详
He died well.
如果你有什么事情我们能为你做 任何事你需要的话...
If there's anything we can do for you, anything you need...
非常欣赏你的善意
It's so kind of you to ask.
你的幸福是我最关心的
Your well-being is my chief concern.
谢谢 我是有点恐惧
Thank you. I have been so scared.
- 但现在已经没有了 - 没有了？
- But I'm not anymore. - No?
安东尼把你描绘成一个残忍的怪物
Antony painted you as a cruel monster.
但实际不是这样
But it is not so.
我感觉你是一个正直的好人
I sense that you are a good and honest man.
- 我说的没错 是吧？- 没错
- I'm not wrong, am I? - No.
我和我的孩子都能确保安全
My children and I are perfectly safe.
- 是的 - 那小恺撒呢？
- You are. - Even Caesarion?
他只是个孩子 不会对我有什么威胁的
He's just a boy. He's no threat to me.
我继续戴着王冠 我仍然是埃及的女王
I keep my crown. I remain queen of Egypt.
你是埃及人
You are Egypt.
我怎能取代你呢
How could I replace you?
我已经很满足了
I am content.
我们会成为好朋友的
We shall be good friends.
会的
We shall.
作为朋友 你能帮我一个忙吗
As a friend, would you grant me one favor?
- 当然 - 跟我一起去罗马
- Of course. - Come with me to Rome.
让罗马的人民看到
Let the Roman people see and rejoice
埃及和恺撒和解了 让他们欢欣鼓舞
that Egypt and Caesar are reconciled.
我很乐意
I would like that very much.
或许是在明年夏天 当我们悼念安东尼时
Perhaps next summer, when our mourning for Antony is done.
是的
Yes.
或者也许会更快些
Or perhaps sooner.
我的船又大又舒适
My ship is large and comfortable.
你真好 我得和我的司祭商量一下
It's so good of you. I shall have to consult my priests.
- 在经历死亡后的一次旅行 - 请吧
- A voyage so soon after a death... - Please.
你带上我 还待我如宾 已经是对我很大的尊敬了
You would be doing me an immense honor by coming with me as a guest.
我会一直心存感激
I would be eternally grateful.
- 我怎能拒绝 - 当然 还有孩子们
- How can I refuse? - And the children, of course.
你必须得带着孩子
You must bring the children.
自然
Naturally.
小恺撒一再渴望去看看罗马
Caesarion is longing to see Rome again.
好的
Good.
- 我们明天起航 - 这么快？
- We sail tomorrow. - So soon?
风向正好适合 推迟的话就不好了
The winds are with us. Would be a shame to delay.
那就明天吧
Tomorrow, then.
关上门
Close the doors!
对不起 亲爱的
I'm sorry, my love.
我太想活着了
I was hungry to live.
但你对那个男孩的看法是对的
But you were right about that boy.
他是个怪物
He's a monster.
他只是想让我活着 把我囚禁起来 向我炫耀
He only wants me alive to parade me in chains
一群乌合之众来鄙视我
for a mob to spit on.
我骗你是没有什么目的的
I lied to you for nothing.
请不要生我的气了
Please don't be angry with me.
把那个老女人带来
Bring the old woman.
她是个精明的角色 是吧
She's a sharp little piece.
她在什么地方都没有在牢里好
She'll look well in nothing but chains.
我们在那儿就该绑架了她
We should have taken her there and then.
她都主动来了 还绑架她啊
Why abduct her when she'll come of her own accord?
如果她追随马克·安东尼死了呢
And what if she follows Mark Antony instead?
她为了活下来而背叛了安东尼 现在会良心发现吗？
She betrayed Antony so that she might live. Why would she lose heart now?
你可以从人们的态度上感觉到
You can have that effect on people.
不 我对她是又温和又讲理的
No, I was all sweetness and light with her.
很有魅力
Charm itself.
是的 那是你做的最令人沮丧的行为
Yes. That is your most disheartening manner.
颠茄素药效不快
The belladonna is not fast...
但疼痛感最弱
but it is least painful.
是的 是的 我知道
Yes. Yes, I know.
哪个能让人死得好看一点？
Which leaves one looking best?
我想要既不会膨起来也不会变色的
I want no bloating or discoloration.
- 蛇可以 但... - 快吗
- The snake, but... - Is it quick?
40次呼吸后断气
40 breaths.
用蛇吧
The snake, then.
看起来不太像啊
It doesn't look like much.
塞思表弟带来的那条是绿色的
The one that took Cousin Seth was green.
- 你记得吗 - 毒性差不多
- Do you remember? - They vary.
这条就够用了
This is the needful animal.
哪儿是最佳部位
Where's the best spot?
手腕或胸部 都行
Wrist or breast, no matter.
谢谢
Thank you.
在你随我去之前 我要确定孩子们都是安全的
Make sure the children are safe before you follow me.
是的 陛下
Yes, Majesty.
现在...咬
Now... bite.
没有感觉
Nothing.
有了
Oh, yes.
她会带你走向生命的终结
It goes away toward the end.
你...
You...
有个腐烂的灵魂
have a rotten soul.
她说了什么
What did she say?
她说我有一个腐烂的灵魂
She said I had a rotten soul.
去找那些孩子
Find the children!
小恺撒已经和卢修斯·乌利纳斯一起逃跑了
Caesarion has escaped with Lucius Vorenus.
这个男人不再忠心了
The man turns loyalty into a vice.
天理何在 他们应该已经离开了？
Any notion where they might have gone?
埃及是个很大的国家
Big country, Egypt.
即便是现在 如果乌利纳斯和那个男孩投降的话
Even now, I would be happy to forgive Vorenus
我也会原谅他
if he surrendered himself and the boy.
- 他已经做了决定 - 是的
- He's made his choices. - Yes.
只要你能和他谈谈 那就仅是那个男孩要去死 波罗
It's a shame when it's just the boy needs to die. If only you could talk to him, Pullo.
我相信你能的
I'm sure you could persuade him of the right course to take.
- 得先找到他 - 是的
- Have to find him first. - Yes.
我能找到他
I could look for him.
那你为什么还不去呢
Why don't you do that?
当我重获属于我的地方
When I recover my rightful place
我可以保证你会得到应得的奖赏
I shall be sure that you are properly rewarded.
你可以挑选一个省去统治 并且要这个国家的任何一个女人
You may choose a province to govern and any woman of the court.
谢谢
Thanks.
那样的生活已经不会再有了 你最好忘记它
That life is over. It's best you forget about it.
荒谬 我母亲会把事情都安排好的
Nonsense. My mother would set things aright.
我很怀疑
I doubt it.
我想知道我父亲怎能容忍他身边 有一个如此悲观的人
I wonder my father tolerated such a pessimist around him.
我不会和你谈这个话题了
There'll be no more talk of that sort.
只是一只鸟
It's just a bird.
以前我从未在晚上还待在沙漠里
I've not been in the desert at night before.
我很不高兴
It does not please me.
我们不该再这样了
We shall not do this again.
去睡会儿吧 明天还要远行
Get some sleep. We've got a long ride tomorrow.
- 我想睡的时候会去睡的 - 你该在我叫你睡的时候就睡
- I will sleep when I like. - You will sleep when I tell you.
怎么了
What's wrong?
- 现在怎么样了 - 还不错 你呢
- How's it going? - Not so bad. You?
差不多吧
Same.
我从未想过那个私生子 再次对我怒目而视
I never thought I'd see that ugly bastard glaring down at me again, though.
我知道你记得的
I knew you'd remember.
- 是他吗 - 是他
- This is him, then? - This is him.
这个人是谁
Who is this man?
- 叫提图斯·波罗 - 你没有礼数
- Name's Titus Pullo. - I do not like your manner.
他很帅 是吧
Handsome, isn't he?
我母亲有什么消息吗
What news of my mother?
她死了 自杀的
She's dead. Killed herself.
死亡的最好方式 值得景仰
Best way to go. Honorable.
别碰我
Do not touch me!
他会长大的
Thought he'd be bigger.
有十个军团在找他
There are ten legions out looking for him.
西向非洲所有的道路
Patrols on all the roads west to Africa,
尼罗河所有港口都有人巡逻
all the Upper Nile ports.
唯一一条路就是去南方
The only way to go is south.
那我们能穿过沙漠返回
So we can cut back across the desert
朝大瀑布下的河走去
towards the river at the cataracts.
我和你们一直到朱迪亚 然后你们从那儿可以找艘船
I'll go with you as far as Judea, you can get a ship from there.
如果想的话 也可以买一艘 他母亲给了我一大笔钱
You can buy a ship if you want. His mother gave me a heavy purse.
你不和我们一起吗
You'll not come with us?
不 我可能会去东部
No, I'll head out east maybe.
那里也许需要士兵的
They always need soldiers out there.
也许你的身份人家不敢收
Probably won't even make it out of Egypt.
孩子们怎么样
How are the children?
很好
Well enough.
大乌利娜和莱德在奥波拿神庙里
Vorena the elder is at the temple of Orbona with Lyde.
卢修斯成了石匠的学徒
Lucius got apprenticed to a stonemason.
石匠？现在是不错的行业
Stonemason? Now that's a decent trade.
他十分想从军
He's on fire to be a soldier.
- 你不会鼓励他的 是吧 - 当然不会
- You're not encouraging him, are you? - No, course not.
小乌利娜 现在...
Vorena the younger, now...
她有点凶
she's a little tiger.
还是话不多 但是...
Still doesn't speak much, mind, but...
开始学着经营酒馆了
practically runs the tavern.
任何人行为不端的 她就会给人家颜色看看
Anyone misbehaves, she gives 'em a look like Medusa on the rag.
盖娅呢
And Gaia?
- 结局不太好 - 不好？
- That didn't end so well. - No?
很长的一个故事
Long story.
你什么时候回来的 我们都没得到你要回来的消息
When did you return? We had no news of your arrival.
我们今早在奥斯提亚靠岸的 我直接来这儿了
We docked this morning at Ostia. I came directly here.
母亲 安东尼死了
Mother, Antony is dead.
自杀的
By his own hand.
亲眼所见
I see.
谢谢你告诉我
Well, thank you for telling me.
祝贺你 你现在像国王一样了
My congratulations. You're as good as king now.
不是国王 只是第一公民罢了
Not king. Merely first citizen.
你要些点心和水吗
Would you care for some refreshments and water?
不了 谢谢
Thank you, no.
我很高兴看到你没难过 现在就悲伤是不得当的
I'm glad you're not upset. A display of grief now would have been impolitic.
当然
Of course.
我没打算悲伤
I've no intention of grieving.
那么 这些孩子们都是谁啊
So, who are the children?
他们是安东尼的孩子 赫利俄斯和塞勒涅
They're Antony's children...Helios and Selene.
战利品
Trophies.
可怜的小东西
Poor things.
或许你会愿意为我照顾他们
Perhaps you will look after them for me.
据我所知 他们很可爱的
They seem amiable enough, as far as I can tell.
这将会是件善事
It would be the charitable thing to do.
好心的屋大维叔叔选择了宽恕
Kindly Uncle Octavian shows mercy.
人民会喜欢这些的
People will love it.
聪明 聪明绝顶啊
Clever. No end to your cleverness.
你杀了另外的一个 是吗？小恺撒？
You murdered the other one, did you? Caesarion?
还没
Not yet.
我希望 会很快
Soon, I hope.
他只想连本代利得到 是整个事情起先都是你的错
He only offers to parley and says the whole thing was your fault in the first place
而我和他应该维护和平
and that me and him should make peace.
- 那你怎么做的 - 我用头撞了他
- What did you reply? - I head-butted the cunny
- 并且把他舌头咬了出来 - 那就代表不同意了 是吧
- and bit his tongue out. - Took that as a no, then, did he?
- 你咬了他的舌头？- 是的
- You bit out his tongue? - I did.
- 尝起来像鸡肉 - 真恶心
- Tasted like chicken. - That is disgusting.
15个金币赌我杀的比你多 最好保持清醒 可能要流血了
Cack. 15 gold says I kill more than you. Best keep clear, boy, it's gonna get wet.
等等 我们可以不用动武
Wait, we can talk our way past.
老天
Gerrae.
一旦说出去 我们就惨了
As soon as his majesty opens his mouth, we're cooked.
- 我们去处理掉他们 - 不 这是命令
- Let's just go at 'em. - No. That's an order.
还是和以前一样的爆脾气 但又谨慎小心
Grumpy and cautious as ever.
就像一只老牧羊犬 说你呢
Like an old sheepdog, you.
你好啊 队长
Salve, Captain.
- 你们是罗马人吗 - 是的
- Romans, are you? - We are.
那边应该没多少罗马人吧 你们做什么的？
Don't see many citizens out here. What's your business?
- 猎杀斯芬克斯 - 没听说过什么斯芬克斯
- Hunting sphinxes. - No such thing as sphinxes.
- 别胡说八道 - 我们是粮食批发商 去孟斐斯
- Now you tell us. - We're grain merchants.
我们刚刚迷路了
We're on the road to Memphis. We've just lost our way.
- 粮食批发商 - 是的
- Grain merchants. - Yeah.
迷路了
Lost your way.
- 你叫什么名字 - 埃涅阿斯
- What's your name, boy? - Aeneas.
- 你这奴隶有点傲慢啊 - 他就这个样
- A bit haughty for a slave. - He is.
我教训过他 让他规矩点 可是不起作用
I beat him regular, but it doesn't do any good.
走吧
On your way, then.
请用您的宽容护佑我们 神圣的君王
我会的
我告诉过你
I told you.
下来
Get down!
车底下
Get under!
他没事吧？
Is he all right?
很严重 他会好的
I've seen worse. He'll be fine.
- 不 我完了 - 傻瓜 你是个大姑娘了
- No, I'm done. - Gerrae, you big girl.
只是一些擦伤
It's just a few scratches.
我们只需要在哪儿躺下休息一会儿
We just need to lay up somewhere for a rest.
过几天 你就又能跑能跳了
A couple of days, you'll be back on your feet.
- 带我回家 - 啊 回家
- Take me home. - Home.
到家还有很长的路 最好我们只...
Home's a long way. It's best we just...
我不想死在肮脏的山洞里
I don't want to die in this fucking shithole.
我想见见我的孩子
I want to see my children.
带我回家
Take me home.
好吧 兄弟 好吧
All right, brother. All right.
来吧
We'll do that.
[一个月后]
赫利俄斯 别跟安东尼娅捣乱
Helios, stop chasing Antonia.
你选好衣服了吗
So, have you chosen a dress?
我认为你应该穿蓝色的那件
I think you should wear that blue thing.
我不去
I'm not going.
- 这不是选择题 - 我不舒服
- It's not a matter of choice. - I don't feel well.
不足为奇 火神烧你你都不会有反应了
No wonder. You could choke Vulcan in here.
今天是你的胜利 也是他的
Today is your triumph as much as his.
作为第一公民的母亲 你应该高兴才对
Mother to the first citizen, you should be happy.
万岁
Hooray.
我一生都在看着你为了这一刻而奋斗
All my life, I've watched you strive for this moment.
看看你
Look at you.
很有趣 不是吗
It's amusing, isn't it?
我不知道如果你放弃的话 我该怎么做
I don't know what I shall do if you give up.
今天我们庆祝
Today we celebrate
我们尊敬的罗马最高执政官
the glory of our beloved imperator
盖厄斯·屋大维·恺撒
Gaius Octavian Caesar!
以及至高无上重获新生的我们的共和国
And the glorious rebirth of our republic!
在这三个小时里 所有的贸易都停止
At the third hour, all trading will cease!
为了这神圣的仪式 必须清理交通
The Sacred Way must be cleared of traffic!
所有违规者都将受到鞭打
Servile violators will be whipped!
- 会有拷打俘虏吗 - 当然
- Will there be captives tortured? - Oh, sure.
- 你确定你不回来了？- 我已经看到了胜利 我不会...
- Are you sure you won't come? - I've seen a triumph, I don't...
你们三个 去接车
You three, upstairs, tend to the cart.
- 波罗 - 你回来了
- Pullo. - You're back!
这是埃涅阿斯 一个朋友
This is Aeneas, a friend.
- 保佑你 - 他来自埃及
- Blessings. - He's from Egypt.
孩子们 我把你们的父亲带回来了
Children, I brought your father home.
- 你为什么把他带到这里来 - 他想看看你们
- Why did you bring him here? - He wants to see you.
他已经受伤了
He's been wounded.
他可能快要死了
He's going to die, likely.
他本应该几周前就死了 但他想回家
He should've died weeks ago, but he wanted to get home.
不然的话不会坚持那么久
Won't last long now.
谢谢 波罗
Thank you, Dr. Pullo.
你还醒着吗 承认了吧
You're awake, then? Make up your mind.
- 莱德 - 你好
- Lyde. - Hello.
孩子们在哪 孩子们在哪
Where are the children? Where are the children?
别动 别动
Lie still. Lie still.
他们不想看到我
They don't want to see me.
我懂的
I understand.
好吧 他们太固执了
That's all right. They're stubborn.
像他们的母亲一样固执
Stubborn like their mother.
休息一下
Rest.
波罗...
Pullo.
那是什么
What's that?
屋大维·恺撒
Octavian Caesar.
他今天班师回国了 好有气势的游行
He's making his official return today. Big parade.
真有趣 我想我快要死了
That's funny. I thought I was dying.
父亲
Father?
女士们 我们要立刻离开了
Ladies, we shall be taking our places very shortly.
我希望你们已经准备好了
I hope you're all ready.
我很抱歉阿提亚不在这儿
I'm sorry Mother Atia could not be here.
恐怕我的丈夫会把这当成一种耻辱
I'm afraid my husband will take it as an insult.
- 不会的吧 - 我知道 我知道她很脆弱
- It isn't meant as such. - I know. I know how fragile she is.
但是屋大维已经很小心地处理这些公共事务了
But dear Octavian is so touchy about these public events.
每件事都会是这样
Everything must be just so.
他已经很听从你的意见了
He has such faith in your judgment.
我相信如果你为她说好话 他一定会宽恕她
I'm sure he'll forgive her if you speak kindly of her.
我会的 我会的
I will, I will.
时间到了 按顺序排队
It is time. In order of precedence, please.
女士们
Hello, ladies.
母亲
Mother.
让我们结束这场闹剧 好吗？
Yes, here I am. Let's just get this charade over with, shall we?
- 抱歉？- 怎么了？
- Excuse me? - Yes?
请恕我直言
I don't mind, really,
我应该排第一个
but it is I who should go first.
司祭会向您解释的
You will find if you consult the priests,
执政官的妻子 排首位
the wife takes precedence.
我不管什么狗屁司祭不司祭
I don't give a fuck what the priests say.
你算什么东西 敢走在我前面
I'll not let a vicious little trollop like you walk ahead of me.
我第一个
I go first.
您当然可以 您的身份尊贵
I take no offence, of course. You are not yourself.
我知道你在想什么
I know who you are.
我能看出来
I can see you.
你在暗暗发誓 总有一天 你要毁掉我
You're swearing now that someday you'll destroy me.
记住 已经有五个和你一样的女人
Remember, far better women than you
自己吞掉了恶果
have sworn to do the same.
现在跟我来吧
Go and look for them now.
凯撒 凯撒 凯撒
Caesar! Caesar! Caesar!
波罗
Pullo.
- 我们都以为你死了 - 没有
- We'd given you up for dead. - No.
有一天或许会的 但不是现在
One of these days maybe, but not yet.
我很高兴你还活着
Well, I'm very glad to see you alive.
老朋友又再见了
Old friends are a rare commodity.
我们的战斗旅程漫长而艰辛
It's been a long road we have traveled together.
是的
It has.
我派你去找小恺撒
I sent you to find Caesarion.
- 有结果吗 - 找到了
- What happened? - I found him.
- 他死了 - 被谁杀的
- He's dead. - You're certain?
- 自杀的 - 怎么自杀的
- Killed him myself. - How?
- 割喉 - 在哪里？
- Cut his throat. - Where was this?
沙漠里
In the desert, some 40-odd miles south of Alex.
本想把尸体运回来
I brought his head to show you, but it went bad.
但是已经不成样子了 所以埋了
Didn't look like anyone. So I tossed it.
卢修斯·乌利纳斯呢？
And Lucius Vorenus?
没找到
Didn't make it.
可惜
That's a shame.
- 是啊 - 他这人很不错
- It is. - He was a good man.
我猜你正等着我奖赏你呢
I suppose you'll be wanting your reward, then.
我可没这么想 我能拒绝吗
I hadn't thought of that. Wouldn't say no.
怎么样了
So?
他相信了
He bought it.
奥西里斯(古埃及神话中司阴府之神) 兄弟
Brother Osiris,
赐我活着并向他的脸上吐痰
let me live to spit in his face
让他牢记这一天
and remind him of this day.
我给你说了多少遍了 别尽说废话
Didn't I tell you there'd be no more of that blather?
废话 这是我的秘密任务
Blather? It is my sacred duty.
用我的鲜血为母亲报仇
By my blood, I'll not rest until I have avenged my mother
恢复我父亲的荣耀和尊严
and redeemed my father's name.
听着 关于你的父亲
Listen, about your father...